INVENTORY OF THE ROBERT VALANAY CORRESPONDENCE, 1921-1978
The Getty Research Institute
- Letters received, 1921-1978, Series I.; ca. 1600 items
  - Jaguer, Edouard, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Typed letter concerns the new journal Rixes and the urgent need for a translation.
  - Janis, Sidney, 1945, 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    3 letters, 4 invitations and 3 New Year's cards.
  - Jean, Marcel, 1950-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    6 letters, 29 cards and postcards, and 4 New Year's cards. Most of the cards are from holiday trips, written in a charming, humorous and intimate style.
  - Jouglet, Ren, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    4 handwritten letters with letterhead from Les Editions des Portiques.
  - Jouty, Michel, 11 Feb 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kandinsky, Nina, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Klee-Palyi, Flora, 1933-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    10 letters, 3 postcards.
  - Kleinfilm-foto, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1 letter in German.
  - Koehlers, K. F., 1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kolney, Fernand, 1929, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - La Polmique, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lachvrel, Frdric, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    5 handwritten letters and 3 cartes-de-visite.
  - Lartigue, Jean, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1 handwritten letter, letterhead "Cahier Du Sud."
  - Le Club franais du livre, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1 letter, concerns a translation.
  - Le Surralisme Permanent (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Table of contents.
  - LeFebvre, 1966, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lvis-Mano, Guy, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1 handwritten letter, agrees to publish a manuscript by Valanay in Editons GLM.
  - Librairie La Hune, 1932-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    8 letters. The first few letters concern Valanay's contribution to La Hune.
  - Librairie Matin Flinker, 11 Jun 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lolie, Bernard, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Louys, R., 18 Jan 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1 letter on Cahiers du Sud stationary.
  - Lubies, H., 30 Mar 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    TLS 3/30/36.
  - Malet, Leo, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Malkine, Malkine, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mangaut, Raymond, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    1 handwritten letter and a card.
  - Marc, Fernand, 1929-1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    42 letters and 14 postcards (some by his wife Gabrielle). Marc, director of Sagesse, publishes Valanay's poetry and does not hesitate to offer constructive criticism. As time passes, they become close friends.
  - Marchand, Jean, Jos, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Marcoussis, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Maret, Jacques, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mariol, Henri, 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Le Progrs du Nord, 5 handwritten letters.
  - Mason, Bill, 1952-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    15 letters and 10 New Years cards. Mason also works for Shell and is currently working on a film about the history of the automobile. Mason's letters are warm and affectionate.
  - Massot, Pierre de, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    1 handwritten letter and a postcard.
  - Matarasso, Henri, 1952, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mathiez, F.T., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Maublanc, Jean-Daniel, 1941, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mauer, Leo, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Maury, Imprimeries, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    7 letters.
  - McLaughlin, Nuala, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mehring, Walter, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    New Years card.
  - Meilland, Ren, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Messinger, Sylvie, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    card.
  - Meyer, Andr, 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    10 handwritten letters and 3 carte-de-visite. Meyer, a German scholar, is enthusiastic about Valanay's translation of Grabbe's "Scherz, Satire und Ironie."
  - Michelet, Victor-Emile, 1927-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mock, Jean-Yves, 1953-1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    12 handwritten letters and 3 cards. Mock manages the Hanover gallery in London and keeps Valanay informed about the exhibitions, occasionally asking for assistance with translations.
  - Monod, Pierre, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Morel, A. et Cie, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Morel, Robert, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Morse, Walter, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    5 handwritten letters and 3 cards.
  - Moza, Andr, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Neergaarde, Beate, ca. 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Noll, Marcel, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Normanville, Peter, de, 1950, 1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    5 handwritten letters and 2 cards.
  - O'Connoll, Aidan, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    7 letters. O'Connoll works for Shell-Bern and met Valanay during the latter's visit to Dublin. Valanay asks O'Connoll for a copy of Dylan Thomas's poems. Their correspondence is personal and chatty; O'Connoll repeatedly invites Valanay and his wife to Ireland.
  - Obaldia, Ren de, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Oppenheim, Meret, 1970-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    13 handwritten letters and 15 cards. Oppenheim thanks Valanay for a translation - presumably "Rves du cosmos" - that he did for her. Valanay sends her a volume of his poems. There is also a question of publishing Wolfgang Paalen's letters but, because of their personal nature, Oppenheim declines. With 6 invitations to Oppenheim's exhibitions.
  - Orenstein, Gloria, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Owens, Noragh, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ozenfant, Amde, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pach, Walter, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Painlev, Jean, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Parisot, Henri, 1935-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    72 handwritten letters. The correspondence begins in an amicable fashion with an exchange of information and comments on various projects, however, in 1938, they have a falling out with Valanay taking Bellmer's side which Parisot apparently finds unacceptable. The correspondence resumes in 1945. Parisot is now the editor of L'Age d'or and wants to publish Valanay's translation of Grabbe's "Scherz, Satire und Ironie." So the correspondence continues with Parisot (who is involved with various journals: Fontaine, Les Quatre Vents, Les Cahiers du Sud) soliciting poems and translations from Valanay. They often deal with technical questions of translation, little known German poets and a rather long discussion, lasting several letters, of Parisot project to publish an Anthologie de la posie humoristque. There is also mention of common friends such as Eluard, Bellmer, Ernst and Marcel Jean.
  - Parrot, Louis, 1928-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    7 handwritten letters and 2 cards.
  - Pastoureau, Henri, 1936, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Paulhan (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Exhibition information.
  - Pauvert, Jean-Jacques, 1946, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Penrose, Roland (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3 handwritten letters and TLS from 2/17/1937 to 4/11/1977.
  - Perceau, Louis, 1931-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    18 handwritten letters. Their exchange begins with literary questions about different editions, bibliographical issues and so forth. However, as the war continues, their correspondence becomes increasingly occupied with the procurement of vegetables, their price and quality.
  - Prichard, Pierre, ca. 1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    4 handwritten letters apparently from about 1940. Prichard, an aspiring writer, is in the French army and appreciates the intellectual exchange that his correspondence with Valanay provides him. He seems to have known George Hugnet as well as Paul Eluard.
  - Pernot, Hubert, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Petithory, Chantal, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Death announcement.
  - Picabia, Francis, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    1 handwritten letter, card and "pneumatique."
  - Picon, Mme, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Bibliothque des arts dcoratifs.
  - Poupard-Lieussou, Yves, 1955-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    8 handwritten letters and 4 cards.
  - Prour, Octav, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Copy of a typed letter.
  - Queneau, Raymond, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    4 letters. Queneau, working at Gallimard, officially declines Valanay's translation of Grabbe.
  - Rabin, Jean-Franois, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Raemisch, Erich, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ray, Man, ca. 1950s-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    5 cards.
  - Richard, Elie, 18 Nov 1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Richter, Hans, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Road, Sinclair, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    2 handwritten letters and a Christmas card.
  - Road, Sinclair (Box 3, Folder 2)
    TLS 11/17/1950.
  - Roch, Henri-Pierre (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Card from 2/4/1950.
  - Roinard, Napolon, ca. 1923-1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    64 handwritten letters. About half are undated but seem to be from the same period. Roinard, prsident d'honneur des potes et conteurs normands, is passionately involved in the research and promotion of Norman authors. He also apologizes to Valanay for the "scandal" of his non-acceptance into the syndicat of Norman poets. The two discuss all manner of literary topics, common friends, and projects mostly having to do with the promotion and publication of Norman writers such as Pourot, Meunier, Humbert, Hamel, Brulat, Biage and so forth.
  - Rosey, Guy, 1930-1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    16 handwritten letters. This correpondence is an amicable exchange between poets who seem to have appreciated each others efforts.
  - Roubaix, Franois de, 20 Nov 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rouveyre, Andr, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Salmon, Andr, 1927-1935 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    3 handwritten letters. With a manuscript copy of poem "Der Dichter In Der Mansarde."
  - Saltas, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sanouillet, Michel, 1950-1953, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    12 letters. An interesting exchange as Sanouillet begins putting together his book on the history of Dada. Also includes his son's birth announcement and New Year's card from 1955.
  - Schwarz, Arthur, 14 Feb 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Schwitter, Ernst, 3 Aug 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Seckel, Hlne, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    2 typed letters; would like to photograph Valanay's complete run of 291.
  - Segolat, Roger, J., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    1 handwritten letter. Segolat wrote a book on Eluard and used Valanay's photographs without attribution.
  - Servant, S., 1 Apr 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Seuphor, Michel, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    1 handwritten letter and 3 cards.
  - Sinot (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Copy of a notary's letter concerning the dispersal of the Marquis de Sade's possessions dated 27 Jan 1815 and a photograph of de Sade's door in Vaucluse.
  - Socit franaise des traducteurs, 1958-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    5 typed letters and a memograph.
  - Solidor, Susy, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stendial, Renata, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Strecker, Paul, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Supervielle, Jules, 28 Apr 1931 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tanguy, Yves, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    1 handwritten letter on Gradiva stationary.
  - Thvenin, Paule, ca. 1949 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    6 letters, 3 about Bilboquet.
  - Tracol, H., 1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Treillard, L., 23 Dec 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Tschischold, Jan, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Tuchman, Emile, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Valanay, Brigitte, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Valanay, George, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Valanay, Mireille, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Verdier, Henri, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    9 handwritten letters.
  - Verlag, Gallus, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    2 typed letters in German.
  - Vesselo, Arthur, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vtiste, Andr, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vidal, J., undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    5 handwritten letters.
  - Villon-Duchamps, Jacques, 1929-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    9 handwritten letters. Short letters concerning artistic questions on cubism and other literary matters.
  - Vingtime Sicle (XX sicle), 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    9 letters.
  - Vordemberge-Gildewart, Nicolas, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wachsmann, Paul, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Waldberg, Patrick, 10 Jun 1963-9 Jan 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    4 cards.
  - Wehrlin, Franois, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wise, David, 24 Nov 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wock, Helmut, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    5 handwritten letters in German.
  - Wolf, E., 1932 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Zayas, R. de., 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Manuscripts and photographs, ca. 1932-1978, Series II.; 9 folders
  Series contains manuscripts, including translations, and a few letters by Valanay, as well as ca. 50 photographs, most presumably taken by Valanay. Also clippings and 5 manuscripts by others.
  - Manuscripts and letters: Valanay, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    2 handwritten letters to Louis Parrot concerning Parrot's unwillingness to lend him certain surrealist journals.
  - Biographical notice (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Biblioteque nationale, 26 Feb 1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    1 handwritten letter to the "Administrateur" of the BN concerning permission to review Sade's manuscript in the "Enfer."
  - Letters between Valanay to Hbertot, 17 Oct 1931-10 Apr 1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    9 typed letters concerning making a copy of a recording of Apollinaire and 8 typed letters from Hbertot responding to Valanay.
  - Translations, essays and notes by Valanay (Box 3, Folder 6)
    A group of 21 German poems translated by Valanay for Parisot's Anthologie de la Posie humoristique. Two short essays on Marcel Jean and essay entitled "Introduction" on the romantic writer Ludwig Tieck. Notes by Valanay on Cravan's journal Maintenant.
  - Translation by Valanay (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Partial translation of Essay on Woman in Three Epistles into French from English by Valanay
  - Articles (Box 3, Folder 7)
    on Andr Breton, Jean Paulhan and various other topics.
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 1)
    2 Dance hall pictures, 12 portraits of Mme and M. Valanay, 6 nude model pictures in a studio (dealer speculates that it might be Breker's studio), 10 photos of women on a beach (Valanay's wife Henriette is one of the women in these pictures, another may be Germaine Hugnet), 19 pictures taken at Eluard's Domaine du Percq in 1934 of Eluard, Nutsch, Germaine and George Hugnet and Henriette Valanay, 3 pornographic postcards. Valanay presumably took most of these pictures.
  - Manuscripts by others, 1933, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    A typed manuscript by Otto Grautoff dated Feb 1933, entitled "Die Literatur. 4 typed manuscripts by Walter J. Moeschlin dated 1948, entitled "Franziskusbild," "Der Sturm," "Der Strom Asmuth," and "Orkeanos." A bibliography of Apollinaire. 4 photographs of a Henry-Dompard.
  - Unidentified letters and cards (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    - Letters, cards and postcards (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Approximately 25 unidentified letters and 25 unidentified cards and postcards
    - Christmas and New Year's Cards (Box 5, Folder 2)
      from friends, colleagues and acquaintances, ca. 85 items.
    - Cards (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Cards (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Cards (Box 5, Folder 5)